<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- This file is part of the DITA Open Toolkit project hosted on 
     Sourceforge.net. See the accompanying license.txt file for 
     applicable licenses.-->
<!-- (c) Copyright IBM Corp. 2005, 2006 All Rights Reserved. -->
<!DOCTYPE task PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Task//EN" "task.dtd">
<task id="addmeta" xml:lang="en-us">
    <title>Adding metadata to elements</title>
    <shortdesc>You can use attributes to provide information about what 
        product, audience, or platform an element applies to, or what revision 
        it belongs to.</shortdesc>
    <prolog>
        <metadata>
            <keywords>
                <indexterm>metadata 
                    attributes<indexterm>adding</indexterm></indexterm>
                <indexterm>adding metadata attributes</indexterm>
            </keywords>
        </metadata>
    </prolog>
    <taskbody>
        <prereq>Before using these attributes, work with your team to agree on 
            a consistent set of values for use across your information set. Do 
            not define your own values without consulting team mates, or your 
            content might not build properly when reusing it.</prereq>
        <context>Use these attributes when you have content within a topic or a 
            map that applies to only one or some of the products, platforms, or 
            audiences for the topic or map as a whole.</context>
        <steps>
            <step>
                <cmd>Find the element you want to provide information for.</cmd>
                <info>If there are not attributes you need in the element, 
                    create a new element inside it, like a ph, which can hold 
                    the attributes instead. </info>
            </step>
            <step>
                <cmd>Enter the value of attribute for the information you want 
                    to provide:</cmd>
                <?Pub Caret?>
                <choicetable>
                    <chrow>
                        <choption>audience</choption>
                        <chdesc>The audience that the element applies to, Could 
                            be a user role (like administrator), experience 
                            level (novice), or combination 
                            (novice-admin).</chdesc>
                    </chrow>
                    <chrow>
                        <choption>platform</choption>
                        <chdesc>The platform (typically hardware, operating 
                            system, or both) that the element applies 
                            to.</chdesc>
                    </chrow>
                    <chrow>
                        <choption>product</choption>
                        <chdesc>The product that the element applies 
                            to.</chdesc>
                    </chrow>
                    <chrow>
                        <choption>otherprops</choption>
                        <chdesc>Any other category of metadata.</chdesc>
                    </chrow>
                    <chrow>
                        <choption>rev</choption>
                        <chdesc>The revision that the element belongs to, if 
                            the topic has been revised and you want to track 
                            what stage particular content was added at.</chdesc>
                    </chrow>
                </choicetable>
            </step>
            <step>
                <cmd>Add a value or values to the attribute.</cmd>
                <stepxmp>For example, audience="novice-admin expert-user" or 
                    platform="wintel".</stepxmp>
            </step>
            <step importance="optional">
                <cmd>For <i>audience</i> or <i>product</i>, add an equivalent 
                    element to the prolog metadata.</cmd>
                <info>You can provide more information about your audience or 
                    product values in the topic's prolog, inside the metadata 
                    element. To ensure consistency, you can define the elements 
                    in one place for the entire information set, and then reuse 
                    them in topics that require them by using the <i>conref</i> 
                    attribute.</info>
            </step>
        </steps>
        <result>Metadata attributes are inherited: they apply to any elements 
            they contain as well. In a table, metadata for a column applies to 
            all the cells in the column.</result>
    </taskbody>
</task>