<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This file is part of the DITA Open Toolkit project hosted on 
     Sourceforge.net. See the accompanying license.txt file for 
     applicable licenses.-->
<!-- (C) Copyright IBM Corporation 2005. All Rights Reserved.
 *-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="ditaotgoals">
  <title>Goals and objectives of the DITA Open Toolkit</title>
  <shortdesc>The DITA Open Toolkit is an implementation of the OASIS DITA 
    Technical Committee&apos;s specification for DITA DTDs and Schemas. The 
    Toolkit transforms DITA content (maps and topics) into deliverable 
    formats.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <p>The long term goal of the DITA Open Toolkit is to provide a high quality 
      implementation for production level output of DITA XML content, built in 
      a professionally-managed project environment by vetted contributors, and 
      tested thoroughly for each Release Candidate.</p>
    <p>The DITA Open Toolkit provides benefits for different roles of 
      users:<ul> <li>Enterprise users (tools to integrate into end-to-end 
      production pipelines)</li> <li>Individuals or small business owners (ease 
      of use for very small scale processing applications; interoperable 
      interchange with enterprise consumers)</li> <li>Consultants (anticipate 
      scenarios for wide range of users; tools to enable consultants to deploy 
      DITA successfully)</li> <li>Vendors (tested OASIS DTDs and stylesheets 
      for editors, transforms for build tools)</li> <li>Academic and 
      educational users (demos of key DITA behaviors and best practices).</li> 
      </ul></p>
    <p>The 1.0 version of the DITA Open Toolkit project lays the basis with an 
      Ant-driven processing architecture and an initial set of XHTML outputs 
      based on code that has been developed and used within IBM for several 
      years. To enable equally high quality for remaining outputs, the project 
      has additional objectives:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Promote the DITA standard in the Information Development 
        community.</li>
      <li>Provide a reference implementation of OASIS DITA standard and provide 
        feedback to DITA standard continuously.</li>
      <li>Use Open Source techniques to create and maintain DITA 
        transformations. </li>
    </ul>
    <section>
      <title>Project objectives</title>
      <p>The project will be managed similarly to any commercial software 
        development project, with requirements gathering, plan validation with 
        stakeholders, scheduled activities, tests, reviews, and builds, with an 
        emphasis on quality.</p>
      <p>The project will emplace a process for tracking all contributions. Any 
        individual or any organization can contribute, but the spirit of the 
        community is personal contribution. IBM as Committer is desirous that 
        all major contributors get appropriate recognition in press releases, 
        etc..</p>
      <p>The DITA Open Toolkit project will track and fix bugs reported against 
        its products, and issue patches based on urgency.</p>
      <p>The DITA Open Toolkit project will track to major version updates of 
        the DTDs/Schemas by the OASIS DITA TC by the quarter following the 
        update. Users should stay with the previous toolkit version for stable 
        function while the new features are being built-out and tested.</p>
      <p>The DITA Open Toolkit project will track to bug fixes of the 
        DTDs/Schemas by the OASIS DITA TC as necessary (many DTD bug fixes tend 
        to have little impact to tools).</p>
      <p>The project agrees with the Open Source motto of &quot;Release early 
        and often&quot; to get wide consensus on issues.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>