<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- (C) Copyright IBM Corporation 2005. All Rights Reserved.
 *--><!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" []>
<topic id="dita-otprojecthome" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>DITA Open Toolkit Project Home</title>
  <shortdesc>This document describes the DITA Open Toolkit project--what the project is, and how to use the site.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>23 Feburary, 2006</title>
      <p>DITA Open Toolkit 1.2 has been released. DITA open toolkit Release 1.2 is a major release to add new functions, fulfill new requirements, make some function enhancements and fix bugs over release 1.1.2.1.</p>
      <p>Please refer to <xref href="../../doc/DITA-relnotes.xml">DITA OT 1.2 release notes</xref> for detailed information about this release. </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>31 August, 2005</title>
      <p>DITA Open toolkit begins to publish the source and binary code under Apache license 2.0 from release 1.1. We provide separate packages for downloading in SourceForege download area.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>18 August, 2005</title>
      <p>DITA Open Toolkit 1.1 has been released. Release 1.1 is a major release to add new functions, fulfill new requirements, make some function enhancements and fix bugs over release 1.0.2.</p>
      <p>Release 1.1 implements the new OASIS DITA 1.0 standard for DITA DTDs and Schemas.</p>
      <p>Release 1.1 also contains a new Eclipse transformation that produces as output a version of DITA XML that can be dynamically rendered in Eclipse Help System. However, this output cannot be used without an special made Eclipse content provider in the Eclipse Help System side.</p>
      <p>Please refer to <xref href="../../doc/DITA-relnotes.xml">DITA OT 1.1 release notes</xref> for detail release information. </p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>03 March, 2005</title>
      <p>DITA Open Toolkit 1.0 is a major upgrade from its predecessor, the developerWorks version known as &quot;dita132.&quot; </p>
      <p>Major improvements from dita132 include:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>A new processing architecture that includes a preprocessing stage</li>
        <li>Full conref resolution in the preprocessor</li>
        <li>Conditional resolution (filtering and flagging) in the preprocessor</li>
        <li>Second pass transformation into final output formats</li>
        <li>Use of Ant and Java for the processing sequence and utility code</li>
        <li>A high-quality transform for XHTML output based on code that IBM has tested and used for the past 5 years</li>
        <li>Translated libraries for generated text in 47 languages (accessed by region and country code) (globalization not fully tested yet)</li>
      </ul>
      <note type="other" othertype="Colophon">The content of this site was sourced as DITA topics, organized using a DITA map, and transformed using the DITA Open Toolkit into HTML.</note>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
