<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2011, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
 "topic.dtd">
<?Pub Sty _display FontColor="red"?>
<topic id="ditaotgoals" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Goals and objectives of the DITA Open Toolkit</title>
<titlealts>
<navtitle>Goals and objectives</navtitle>
</titlealts>
<shortdesc>The long term goal of the DITA Open Toolkit is to provide
a high quality        implementation for production level output of
DITA XML content, built in        a professionally-managed project
environment by vetted contributors, and        tested thoroughly for
each release.</shortdesc>
<body>
<p>The DITA-OT may be used in a variety of ways:<ul>
<li>It may be integrated as one component in a larger end-to-end production
pipeline. The minimal or standard packages are generally best suited
for this use.</li>
<li>It may be used on its own as a complete DITA production system.
Users looking for this will most likely want the Full Easy Install
package.</li>
<li>It may be integrated into vendor tools such as editors or content
management systems, to provide an easy DITA production system. The
minimal package is designed for this type of use.</li>
</ul></p>
<section><title>Project objectives</title><p>The project is managed
similarly to any commercial software development project, with requirements
gathering, plan validation with stakeholders and contributors, scheduled
activities, tests, reviews, and builds, with an emphasis on quality.</p><p>The
project has an established process for tracking all contributions.
Any individual or any organization can contribute; contributions must
adhere to the existing toolkit license(s) and should fit in with the
general goals of the project. All major contributors will get appropriate
recognition in release announcements and on the project home page.</p><p>Bugs
and new feature requests may be submitted through the project page
at github: <xref format="html"
href="https://github.com/dita-ot/dita-ot/issues" scope="external">DITA-OT
Issues at github</xref>. The core project contributors will track
and address bugs reported against its products, and issue patches
based on urgency. The core contributors will also provide feedback
on requests for major new features or changes, but may not be able
to provide development assistance on all requests.</p><p>The DITA
Open Toolkit project will keep up to date with the latest DITA DTD
and Schema updates from the OASIS DITA Technical Committee (owners
of the DITA standard). If bugs are found in the OASIS DTDs or Schemas,
they will be fixed in the toolkit and reported back to OASIS. As OASIS
produces drafts of future versions, the DITA-OT will work to create
early support for new features in order to help test the standard.</p><p>The
project agrees with the Open Source motto of &quot;Release early and
often&quot; to get wide consensus on issues. The project works with
an agile development process, releasing test builds approximately
every month, and encourages feedback on test builds while function
is being developed. We typically put out new stable releases approximately
every six months.</p><?Pub Caret -1?></section>
</body>
</topic>
<?Pub *0000003239?>
