<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2011, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
 "topic.dtd">
<?Pub Sty _display FontColor="red"?>
<?Pub Inc?>
<topic id="fixesandfeatures" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Requesting features and reporting defects</title>
<shortdesc>Defect reports and feature requests may be submitted at
any time through the project page at github. </shortdesc>
<body>
<p>The core project contributors will track and address bugs reported
against the project, and issue patches based on urgency. The core
contributors will also provide feedback on requests for new features
or design changes, but may not be able to provide development assistance
on all requests.</p>
<p>All new bug reports or feature requests should be submitted through
github: <xref keyref="dita-ot-issues"></xref>.</p>
<section><title>Requesting new features</title><p>Requests for new
features may be submitted at any time. The project committers will
have periodic reviews of new feature requests along with other contributors
and interested parties and (when possible) make plans for implementation.</p><p>Generally,
if an existing project developer is interested in a new request, the
item will be assigned to that developer and implemented based on the
developer's schedule. Otherwise, if the request is valid and in line
with project goals, it will be left open for an interested party to
pick up and implement. In some cases requests are best implemented
as a customization (plug-in) outside of the core tools, in which case
the request will be closed with suggested alternatives.</p></section>
<section><title>Defects</title><p>Defect reports may be submitted
at any time using the same process. Project committers will determine
the owner of the relevant components and assign the bug for validation
and disposition. Responses, fixes, and workarounds are generally quickest
if those submitting a defect report are able to include sample files
or clear instructions for reproducing the issue.</p><p>If bugs are
found in the OASIS DTDs or Schemas, they will be fixed in the toolkit
and reported back to OASIS.</p></section>
</body><?Pub Caret -2?>
</topic>
<?Pub *0000002220?>
