<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2011, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
 "topic.dtd">
<?Pub Inc?>
<topic id="projectroles" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Project roles and responsibilities</title>
<titlealts>
<navtitle>Project roles</navtitle>
</titlealts>
<shortdesc>There are several roles in the DITA Open Toolkit open source
project. Each has different rights and obligations.</shortdesc>
<body>
<section id="pm"><title>Project manager (PM)</title><p>The project
manager is n individual responsible for managing this open source
project. The PM is expected to ensure that<ul>
<li>All Projects operate effectively by providing leadership to guide
this project's overall direction and by removing obstacles, solving
problems, and resolving conflicts. </li>
<li>All Project plans, technical documents and reports are publicly
available.</li>
<li>All Projects operate using open source rules of engagement: meritocracy,
transparency, and open participation. These principles work together.
Anyone can participate in this project. This open interaction, from
answering questions to reporting bugs to making code contributions
to creating designs, enables everyone to recognize and utilize the
contributions.</li>
</ul></p></section>
<section id="committer"><title>Committer</title><p>A committer is
expected to influence the Project's development and has write access
to the source code repository. This position reflects a track record
of high quality contributions. Committers oversee the quality and
originality of all contributions.</p></section>
<section id="contributor"><title>Contributor</title><p>A contributor
is an individual who contributes code, fixes, tests, documentation,
or other work that is part of this project. A Contributor does not
have write access to the source code repository. There is no limit
to the scope of such contributions, though any contributors expecting
to donate a large amount of new function to the project is encouraged
to work together with committers in advance.</p></section>
</body>
</topic><?Pub Caret -3?>
<?Pub *0000002130?>
