<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2011, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
 "topic.dtd">
<?Pub Sty _display FontColor="red"?>
<?Pub Inc?>
<topic id="ditaopentoolkitreleaselifecycle" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>DITA Open Toolkit Release management</title>
<titlealts>
<navtitle>Release management</navtitle>
</titlealts>
<shortdesc>The DITA-OT project uses an agile development process,
with roughly four-week development iterations followed by the release
of a full test build that includes all new function developed up to
that point. Roughly twice a year, a final "stable" build will be released.</shortdesc>
<body>
<p>Each iteration begins with a meeting of project contributors. <xref
keyref="contributor-meeting-minutes"></xref> are stored publicly on
the project wiki at github. Active contributors are directly invited
to these meetings, but anybody interested in the toolkit's development
is welcome to attend. If you are interested in contributing or attending
these meetings, please join the dita-ot-developer mailing list and
send a note to the list (or list owners): <xref
keyref="dita-ot-developer"></xref>.</p>
<p>Each iteration kick-off meeting will cover the following topics:<ul>
<li>Discuss any issues from the previous iteration</li>
<li>Specific plans from each contributor for the upcoming iteration,
or for new work that will cover multiple iterations</li>
<li>Design discussion for any significant planned features or fixes</li>
<li>Longer term plans for contributions to the current or following
release</li>
<li>Other project issues or hot topics, as needed, such as changes
to the test and build process, interest from new contributors, etc</li>
<li>For the final iteration before a stable build:<ul>
<li>Evaluate what is allowed in the iteration; the final iteration
typically has no major changes in order to assure quality in the stable
build</li>
<li>Ensure that all release notes are up to date, and other artifacts
will be ready for a final build</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></p>
<p>When an iteration is complete, the build is uploaded to SourceForge.
Test builds are placed in the "Latest Test Build" folder; at the end
of a release cycle, the builds will be loaded to the Stable Release
folder, and the project information is updated to reflect the latest
release.</p>
</body>
</topic><?Pub Caret -1?>
<?Pub *0000002406?>
