<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Reference//EN"
 "reference.dtd">
<reference id="errormessages" xml:lang="en-us">
<title conref="DITA-messages.xml#msgs/title" conaction="pushreplace">Error messages</title>
<shortdesc conref="DITA-messages.xml#msgs/shortdesc" conaction="pushreplace">This topic defines all error messages generated by the
DITA-OT.</shortdesc>
<refbody>
<section id="overview" conref="DITA-messages.xml#msgs/overview" conaction="pushreplace"><p>By convention, messages in the toolkit follow
a simple pattern:<ul>
<li>Message prefix (generally 4 letters) that indicates where the
message comes from; for example, DOTX is used for messages from the
core toolkit XSLT steps.</li>
<li>Message number</li>
<li>Message severity</li>
</ul></p><p>Message severities include:<ul>
<li>I (Informational): the toolkit has encountered a situation that
may not be what you intended, but will not cause problems in processing.</li>
<li>W (Warning): a problem has been encountered which should be corrected.
Processing will generally attempt to recover and continue, but the
results may not be as expected.</li>
<li>E (Error): a more severe problem has been encountered, such as
invalid or missing content. Results will not be as expected.</li>
<li>F (Fatal): processing cannot continue; the problem must be resolved
in order to produce output.</li>
</ul></p><p>Plug-ins may be used to add additional messages into the
toolkit; for more information, see the Developer reference section
of the User Guide. If you would like to rebuild the documentation
to include any newly integrated messages, first run the following
command from the <filepath>DITA-OT/doc/</filepath> directory.</p><codeblock>DITA-OT/doc/ant -f build.xml generate-msg-topic</codeblock><p>After
running the command, rebuild the documentation to your desired output
format. You an also use that same build file to build the full guide
to PDF, XHTML, or HTML Help, all of which will automatically 
recreate this message topic.</p></section>
<simpletable>
<sthead>
<stentry>Individual cells in this table may be used to push additional
explanations for any existing error message into the generated message
topic.</stentry>
</sthead>
<strow>
<stentry>To add additional explanation to any message, add the explanation to this
table in a single sell, and set the the following attributes on the &lt;stentry&gt; tag:<ul>
<li><codeph>conref="DITA-messages.xml#msgs/MESSAGEID-extra"</codeph> -- for example,
use the following to add additional info to message DOTX001F:
<codeph>conref="DITA-messages.xml#msgs/DOTX001F-extra"</codeph></li>
<li><codeph>conaction="pushreplace"</codeph></li>
</ul></stentry>
</strow>
<strow>
<stentry conref="DITA-messages.xml#msgs/DOTA001F-extra" conaction="pushreplace">Additional transform types may be
available if toolkit plug-ins are installed.</stentry>
</strow>
<strow>
<stentry conref="DITA-messages.xml#msgs/DOTA003F-extra" conaction="pushreplace">The args.xsl parameter
(or the /XSL parameter when using the Java command line) was used to specify an
alternate stylesheet for generating XSLT, but that stylesheet could not be loaded.
Please correct the parameter to specify a valid stylesheet.</stentry>
</strow>
<strow>
<stentry conref="DITA-messages.xml#msgs/DOTA004F-extra" conaction="pushreplace">This optional parameter is used
to set an extension used for DITA topic documents in the temporary processing directory. Only
"dita" and "xml" are used during processing.</stentry>
</strow>
</simpletable>
</refbody>
</reference>
