<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
 "topic.dtd">
<?Pub Sty _display FontColor="red"?>
<?Pub Inc?>
<topic id="ditausingxform" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Using DITA transforms</title>
<shortdesc>The core transforms of the DITA Open Toolkit represent an implementation of all
    processing defined by OASIS in the DITA specification.</shortdesc>
<body>
<section id="preprocess">             <title>Pre-process</title><?Pub
Caret -2?><p>A pre-process is done before the main transformation. The input of the pre-process is dita files
        (maps and topics) and the output of the pre-process is often referred to as "normalized"
        dita files. The pre-process stage resolves several common DITA behaviors, such as resolving
        conref attributes, resolving keyref values, and adding links based on the hierarchy and
        relationship tables in a map. The normalized dita files are in a temporary directory. Most
        DITA transforms use this common pre-process setup.</p></section>
<section>       <title>Available core transforms</title><p>A core DITA transform is the basic set of templates that support all the elements of a topic.
        This set is the basis for the following processing of any specialized element. Core
        transforms handle one topic instance, or nested set of topics, at a time. The DITA Open
        Toolkit provides several core transforms:</p>
  <dl id="core-tranforms">
    <dlentry>
      <dt>PDF</dt>
      <dd>PDF output is based on a plug-in that produces XSL-FO output. The XSL-FO output may be
            converted to PDF using an open source tools (Apache FOP) or using commercial tools such
            as RenderX or Antenna House Formatter. This transformation type replaced an older demo
            PDF transform, and is often called "PDF2".</dd>
    </dlentry>
    <dlentry>
      <dt>XHTML</dt>
      <dd>XHTML output is supported together with a variety of XHTML-based navigation types.
        Navigation is not required. The XHTML output contains class values based on the DITA
        elements so CSS files may be used to customize the output style.</dd>
    </dlentry>
    <dlentry>
      <dt>Eclipse Help</dt>
      <dd>Eclipse output is an XHTML based format that also produces navigation and index files
        for use with Eclipse information centers.</dd>
    </dlentry>
    <dlentry>
      <dt>TocJS</dt>
      <dd>The TocJS transformation type includes XHTML output along with JavaScript based frames
        for navigation, including TOC sections that expand and collapse.</dd>
    </dlentry>
    <dlentry platform="windows">
      <dt>HTML Help</dt>
      <dd>Microsoft Compiled HTML Help output produces a compiled help
        (<filepath>.chm</filepath>) file with the XHTML topics, table of contents, and
        index.</dd>
    </dlentry>
    <dlentry>
      <dt>Java Help</dt>
      <dd>Java Help includes a table of contents and index for use with the Java Help
        platform.</dd>
    </dlentry>
    <dlentry rev="1.5.2">
      <dt>OpenDocument (ODT)</dt>
      <dd>ODT is a document format based on the ODF standard, for use with tools like Open
        Office. Support for ODT was added in DITA-OT 1.5.2.</dd>
    </dlentry>
    <dlentry>
      <dt>Rich Text Format (RTF)</dt>
      <dd>RTF output is supported for basic content, but complex markup and some advanced
        features of DITA may not be supported.</dd>
    </dlentry>
    <dlentry>
      <dt>troff</dt>
      <dd>troff based man pages are supported; one man page is generated for each input topic. Note
            that tables are not supported by this transformation type.</dd>
    </dlentry>
  </dl>     </section>
  <!--
<section>       <title>Available special output formats</title><p>Additional
map-driven tools support transforming sets of topics into        
 special output formats, including:<dl><dlentry>
<dt>map2eclipsehelp (map2eclipse.xsl)</dt>
<dd>This          transform generates table of content for help contents
in Eclipse.</dd>
</dlentry><dlentry>
<dt>Web page          (map2htmtoc.xsl)</dt>
<dd>This transform generates a set of web pages          with an index
page that is ready to place on a Web site.</dd>
</dlentry><dlentry>
<dt>map2htmlhelp (map2hhc.xsl map2hhp.xsl)</dt>
<dd>This transform generates hhc and hhp file for the compilation
of          Html Help.</dd>
</dlentry><dlentry>
<dt>map2javahelp          (map2JavaHelpToc.xsl map2JavaHelpMap.xsl)</dt>
<dd>This transform          generates table of content and jhm file
for Java Help.</dd>
</dlentry></dl></p>     </section>
-->
<section>       <title>Invoke the complete transformation</title> 
     <p>The complete transformation including pre-process can be executed by an Ant script. There
        are some examples of simple Ant scripts in the directory
          <filepath>samples/ant_sample</filepath>.</p> 
   </section>
</body>
  <related-links>
    <link href="DITA-ant.xml"/>
  </related-links>
</topic>
<?Pub *0000003228?>
