<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
 "topic.dtd">
<topic id="ditaotgoals" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Goals and objectives of the DITA Open Toolkit</title>
  <titlealts>
    <navtitle>Goals and objectives</navtitle>
  </titlealts>
<shortdesc>The long term goal of the DITA Open Toolkit is to provide
a high quality        implementation for production level output of
DITA XML content, built in        a professionally-managed project
environment by vetted contributors, and        tested thoroughly for
each release.</shortdesc>
<body>
<p>The DITA-OT may be used in a variety of ways:<ul>
<li>It may be integrated as one component in a larger end-to-end production
pipeline. Either the minimal or standard package may be the most suitable
for this use.</li>
<li>It may be used on its own as a complete DITA production system.
Users looking for this will most likely use the Full Easy Install
package.</li>
<li>It may be integrated into vendor tools such as editors or content
management systems, to provide an easy DITA production system. The
minimal package is designed for this type of use.</li>
</ul></p>
<section>       <title>Project objectives</title>       <p>The project
will be managed similarly to any commercial software          development
project, with requirements gathering, plan validation with       
  stakeholders, scheduled activities, tests, reviews, and builds,
with an          emphasis on quality.</p>       <p>The project will
emplace a process for tracking all contributions. Any          individual
or any organization can contribute, but the spirit of the        
 community is personal contribution. IBM as Committer is desirous
that          all major contributors get appropriate recognition in
press releases,          etc..</p>       <p>The DITA Open Toolkit
project will track and fix bugs reported against          its products,
and issue patches based on urgency.</p>       <p>The DITA Open Toolkit
project will track to major version updates of          the DTDs/Schemas
by the OASIS DITA TC.</p>       <p>The DITA Open Toolkit project will
track to bug fixes of the          DTDs/Schemas by the OASIS DITA
TC as necessary (such fixes tend          to have little impact to
tools).</p>       <p>The project agrees with the Open Source motto
of &quot;Release early          and often&quot; to get wide consensus
on issues. The project works with an Agile development process, releasing
test builds approximately every three weeks, and encourages feedback
on test builds while function is being development.</p><?Pub Caret 239?> 
   </section>
</body>
</topic>
<?Pub *0000002639?>
