<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- (c) Copyright IBM Corp. 2005, 2006 All Rights Reserved. -->
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Reference//EN" "..\dtd\reference.dtd">
<reference id="limitations" xml:lang="en-us">
    <title>Known Limitations</title>
    <shortdesc>Below are some known limitations categoried by module within 
        the current release of the DITA Open Toolkit.</shortdesc>
    <refbody>
        <section>
            <title>Transformation to PDF and Word RTF</title>
            <ol>
                <li>The transforming tool will copy the images from DITA source files to the
output directory during the process. In the output file, links to the images
in local directory are provided instead. </li>
                <li>You can change the styles of the output file by using tools in <tm tmclass="special"
tmowner="Microsoft Corporation" tmtype="reg" trademark="Microsoft">Microsoft</tm> Word
rather than specifying the styles before transforming.</li>
                <li>If there is a cross reference referring to an URL in the DITA source file,
the link should be completed defined with the proper internet protocol. For
example, specify <userinput>http://www.ibm.com</userinput> instead
of <userinput>www.ibm.com</userinput>.</li>
                <li>Flagging, revision bar and filtering are not supported in PDF and Word RTF output.</li>
                <li>Morerows attribute of the table element used to generating vertically merged cell is not supported in PDF output.</li>
                <li>Style attributes for table are not supported in Word RTF output.</li>
                <li>Complex cases dealing with lists, such as list in table, table in list and nested list, are not supported in Word RTF and might corrupt the output document.</li>
                <li>Cell missing in table might corrupt table in Word RTF output.</li>
                <li>There might be no output style applied on contents of some tags in Word RTF output compared with other output.</li>
            </ol>
        </section>     
        <section>
            <title>HTML to DITA migration</title>
            <ol>
                <li>Since Xalan doesn't allow to set the public and system IDs 
                    dynamically using a variable, when Xalan is used as the 
                    default XSLT processor, the output will contain:
                    <codeblock>&lt;!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "{$publicid}" "{$systemid}"></codeblock>
                    <p>Suggest to use Saxon as the processor to fix this 
                        problem. For other information on this problem, see 
                        the section "Other general migration notes" in the 
                        first developerWorks article.</p></li>
                <li>Currently, the stylesheet can't handle HTML files within 
                    namespace like below:
                    <codeblock>&lt;html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"></codeblock>
                    <p>You need to remove the <codeph>xmlns</codeph> attribute 
                        before the migration.</p></li>
            </ol>
        </section>
    </refbody>
</reference>