<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
 "topic.dtd">
<?Pub Sty _display FontColor="red"?>
<?Pub Inc?>
<topic id="ditausingxform" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Using DITA transforms</title>
<shortdesc>The core transforms of the DITA Toolkit represent an implementation
of all processing defined by OASIS in the DITA specification.</shortdesc>
<body>
<section id="preprocess">             <title>Pre-process</title><?Pub
Caret -2?><p>A pre-process is done before the main transformation.
The input of the pre-process is dita files (maps and topics) and the
output of the pre-process is often referred to as "normalized" dita
files. The pre-process stage resolves several common DITA behaviors,
such as resolving conref attributes, resolving keyref values, and
adding links based on the hierarchy and relationship tables in a map.
The normalized dita files are in a temporary directory. Most DITA
transforms should use this common pre-process setup.</p></section>
<section>       <title>Available core transforms</title><p>A core
DITA transform is the basic set of templates that support all    
     the elements of a topic. This set is the basis for the following
         processing of any specialized element. Core transforms handle
one topic          instance, or nested set of topics, at a time. The
DITA Toolkit provides several core transforms:<dl><dlentry>
<dt>XHTML</dt>
<dd>DITA topic to XHTML page transform.</dd>
</dlentry><dlentry>
<dt>PDF</dt>
<dd>DITA topic or map to PDF, using XSL Formatting Objects</dd>
</dlentry><dlentry>
<dt>RTF</dt>
<dd>DITA topic or map to RTF; note that the output for RTF is more
limited than for PDF, particularly for tables.</dd>
</dlentry><dlentry>
<dt>TROFF</dt>
<dd>DITA topic to TROFF; complex table markup is not supported by
the TROFF transform</dd>
</dlentry></dl></p>     </section>
<section>       <title>Available special output formats</title><p>Additional
map-driven tools support transforming sets of topics into        
 special output formats, including:<dl><dlentry>
<dt>map2eclipsehelp (map2elipse.xsl)</dt>
<dd>This          transform generates table of content for help contents
in Eclipse.</dd>
</dlentry><dlentry>
<dt>Web page          (map2htmtoc.xsl)</dt>
<dd>This transform generates a set of web pages          with an index
page that is ready to place on a Web site.</dd>
</dlentry><dlentry>
<dt>map2htmlhelp (map2hhc.xsl map2hhp.xsl)</dt>
<dd>This transform generates hhc and hhp file for the compilation
of          Html Help.</dd>
</dlentry><dlentry>
<dt>map2javahelp          (map2JavaHelpToc.xsl map2JavaHelpMap.xsl)</dt>
<dd>This transform          generates table of content and jhm file
for Java Help.</dd>
</dlentry></dl></p>     </section>
<section>       <title>Invoke the complete transformation</title> 
     <p>The complete transformation including pre-process can be executed
by an ant script. There are some examples of simple ant scripts in
the directory <filepath>samples/ant_sample</filepath>. See <xref
href="DITA-antuse.xml"></xref> for more details about Ant processing.</p> 
   </section>
<section></section>
</body>
</topic>
<?Pub *0000003228?>
