<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- This file is part of the DITA Open Toolkit project hosted on 
     Sourceforge.net. See the accompanying license.txt file for 
     applicable licenses.-->
<!-- (c) Copyright IBM Corp. 2004, 2005 All Rights Reserved. -->

<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd">
<topic id="ditausingxform" xml:lang="en-us">
  <title>Using DITA transforms</title>
  <shortdesc>The core transforms of the DITA Toolkit represent the <q>Reference 
    Implementation</q> for processing the standard DITA specification as 
    maintained by OASIS Open.</shortdesc>
  <body>
    <section id="preprocess">
      <?Pub Caret?>
      <title>Pre-process</title>
      <p>A pre-process is done before the main transformation. The input of 
        Pre-process is dita files and the output of Pre-process is also dita 
        files. But the output is in temp directory. Pre-process is the basic 
        for the main transformation, it handles several different processing 
        before the main transformation. Without pre-process, dita topics and 
        map can still be transformed into different outputs, but the features 
        in pre-process such as resolving conref attribute are not available.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Available core transforms</title>
      <p>A core DITA transform is the basic set of templates that support all 
        the elements of a topic. This set is the basis for the following 
        processing of any specialized element. Core transforms handle one topic 
        instance, or nested set of topics, at a time. The DITA Toolkit provides 
        these core transforms:<dl><dlentry> <dt>dita2xhtml.xsl</dt> <dd>DITA 
        topic to HTML page transform.</dd> </dlentry></dl><dl><dlentry> 
        <dt>dita2fo-shell.xsl</dt> <dd>DITA topic to XSL Formatting Object page 
        transform.</dd> </dlentry></dl></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Available special output formats</title>
      <p>Additional map-driven tools support transforming sets of topics into 
        special output formats, including:<dl><dlentry> <dt>Web page 
        (map2htmtoc.xsl)</dt> <dd>This transform generates a set of web pages 
        with an index page that is ready to place on a Web site.</dd> 
        </dlentry><dlentry> <dt>map2htmlhelp (map2hhc.xsl map2hhp.xsl)</dt> 
        <dd>This transform generates hhc and hhp file for the compilation of 
        Html Help.</dd> </dlentry><dlentry> <dt>map2javahelp 
        (map2JavaHelpToc.xsl map2JavaHelpMap.xsl)</dt> <dd>This transform 
        generates table of content and jhm file for Java Help.</dd> 
        </dlentry><dlentry> <dt>map2eclipsehelp (map2elipse.xsl)</dt> <dd>This 
        transform generates table of content for help contents in Eclipse.</dd> 
        </dlentry><dlentry> <dt>map2printout</dt> <dd>Calls topicmerge to 
        consolidate a set of topics into a single entity that is transformed 
        into Formatting Objects (FO), which can be compiled into PDF.</dd> 
        </dlentry></dl></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Invoke the complete transformation</title>
      <p>The complete transformation including pre-process can be excuted by 
        the ant script. There are some examples of simple ant script in 
        directory /ant. The ant target for the transformation which can be 
        called is listed at <xref href="DITA-antuse.xml">Running 
        Ant</xref></p>
    </section>
    <section></section>
  </body>
</topic>