<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- This file is part of the DITA Open Toolkit project hosted on 
     Sourceforge.net. See the accompanying license.txt file for 
     applicable licenses.-->
<!-- (c) Copyright IBM Corp. 2005, 2006 All Rights Reserved. -->
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Reference//EN" "reference.dtd">
<reference id="loghandling" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Problem determination and log analysis</title>
<refbody>
<section>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <p>In the DITA Open Toolkit 1.2 or above, a new logging method is supported 
    to log messages both on the screen and into the log file. The messages on 
    the screen present user with the status information, warning, error, and 
    fatal error messages. The messages in the log file present user with more 
    detailed information about the transformation process. By analyzing these 
    messages, user can know what cause the problem and how to solve it.</p>
  <p>The logging method is based on Ant's Logger &amp; Listener interface. 
    By default, this logging method is disabled, and all the messages occur on 
    the screen just like previous releases.</p>
  <p>To start this new logging method, you need to follow the usage below:
  <ul>
    <li>In Ant command, specify the logger by appendding 
        <codeph>-logger org.dita.dost.log.DITAOTBuildLogger</codeph> in the 
        command parameters, for example: 
        <codeblock>ant sample.web -logger org.dita.dost.log.DITAOTBuildLogger
        </codeblock></li>
    <li>In Java command, the logger is specified internally, so you do not 
        need to specify it again.</li>
  </ul></p>
</section>
<section>  
  <title>Analyze messages on the screen</title>   
  <p>During the building process, some information or messages occur on the
     screen to tell you about the status, warnings, errors, or fatal errors. 
     You need to analyze the messages to solve the problems.
  <ul>
    <li>If the build succeeded with some warning messages on the screen, 
        it means that there are something incorrect within the user input  
        parameters or source DITA files; but you can still get the 
        correct output.</li>
    <li>If the build succeeded with some error messages on the screen, 
        it means that there are something incorrect within the user input 
        parameters or source DITA files; the output maybe not correct.</li>
    <li>If the build failed with fatal error message on the screen, 
        it means that there are something illegal or invalid within the user 
        input parameters or source DITA files; you may get no output, or wrong 
        output.</li>
  </ul>
  </p>
</section>
<section>
  <title>Analyze messages in the log file</title>
  <p>A log file in plain text format is generated in the log directory, 
     which has a name combined with both input file name and transform type. 
     You can open it and find more detailed information, which are helpful 
     for solving problems. You can use the same way introduced above to analyze 
     the messages and solve the problems.</p>
  <p>The log directory can be specified by using the parameter 
    <codeph>/logdir:{args.logdir}</codeph> for the output options.</p>
  <p><note>In some cases, there would be no log file generated:
    <ul>
        <li>You have entered an invalid Ant command or Java command to start 
            the toolkit.</li>
        <li>The log file with the same name in the same directory exists and 
            can not be deleted.</li>
    </ul></note></p>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Turn on debug mode</title>
    <p>Debug mode is supported along with the new logging method. Under debug 
        mode, diagnostic information, such as: environment variables, stack 
        trace, will be logged into the log file. These information can help 
        the user or developer to go deep into the problems and find the root 
        cause.</p>
    <p>By default, the debug mode is disabled. To turn on the debug mode, 
        you need to follow the usage below:
      <ul>
        <li>Append <codeph>-d</codeph> or <codeph>-debug</codeph> in Ant 
            command.</li>
        <li>Append <codeph>/d</codeph> or <codeph>/debug</codeph> in Java 
            command.</li>
      </ul></p>
</section>
<section>
    <title>About message file</title>
    <p>The message file is used to store the detailed log messages, these 
      messages are read dynamically from this file. To ensure those messages 
      can be read correctly during the transform process, the message file 
      should be located properly. In some situations, the toolkit may fails 
      to load the message file due to some exceptions thrown. Please refer to 
      <xref href="DITA-troubleshooting.xml"/> for detailed information.</p>
    <p>For high level users and developers, there is a propery 
      <codeph>args.message.file</codeph> in the toolkit's ant script, it is 
      used to config the message file, you can overide it in your ant script.</p>
    <note>Due to the difference of underly implemetation between Java, And, 
      and XSL, the property <codeph>args.message.file</codeph> is only useful 
      for Java and Ant; To keep the normal function of log handling, you still 
      need to ensure there are files 'resource/messages.xml' and 'resource/messages.dtd' 
      both in the toolkit's root directory and in the directory that you run the 
      toolkit.</note>
</section>
</refbody>
</reference>
