<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- This file is part of the DITA Open Toolkit project hosted on 
     Sourceforge.net. See the accompanying license.txt file for 
     applicable licenses.-->
<!-- (c) Copyright IBM Corp. 2004, 2005 All Rights Reserved. -->

<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN" "concept.dtd">

<concept id="ditafutures" xml:lang="en-us">
  <title>DITA futures</title>
  <shortdesc>Activity on the DITA Open Toolkit project will revolve around 
    maintenance (bug fixes), enhancements (new function based on prioritized 
    requests), demos and experimentation (sandbox activity), and community 
    support (forums, etc.).</shortdesc>
  <conbody>
    <p>DITA Open Toolkit 1.0 is a major upgrade from its predecessor, the 
      developerWorks version known as &quot;dita132.&quot; Because this is a 
      new project with a new name. a new home, and largely new code, and 
      because it is considered production-level code for XHTML output, the 
      project numbering has been initiated at 1.0 for the first built release. 
      The 1.0 version of code is still based on the dita132 DTDs 
      and Schemas.</p>
    <p>Major improvements from dita132 include:<ul> <li>A new processing 
      architecture that includes a new preprocessing stage</li> <li>Full conref 
      resolution in the preprocessor</li> <li>Full conditional resolution 
      (filtering and flagging) in the preprocessor</li> <li>Second pass 
      transformation into final output formats</li> <li>Use of Ant and Java for 
      the processing sequence and utility code</li> <li>A high-quality 
      transform for XHTML output based on code that IBM has tested and used for 
      the past 5 years</li> <li>Translated libraries for generated text in 47 
      languages (accessed by region and country code)</li> </ul></p>
    <section>
      <title>Future plans:</title>
      <p>Future development activity of the DITA Open Toolkit is based on the 
        end goal of providing a complete reference implementation for all core 
        output transforms. The anticipated order of work based on current 
        prioritizations (post 1.0) will be:<ul> <li>1.1: Develop the currently 
        demo-level FO transforms to support production-level, book-like 
        functionality with a generic format that can be easily interfaced for 
        particular corporate styles and branding. This will involve working 
        with the OASIS DITA Technical Committee to validate and endorse the 
        bookmap specialization of DITA map. (roughly matching the DITA TC 1.1 
        plan, based on the OASIS DITA 1.0-level DTDs and Schemas, expected to 
        be a Spec in this timeframe). This version will be based on the OASIS 
        DITA 1.0 level of DTDs and Schemas.</li> <li>1.2 (roughly): Develop the 
        remaining demo-level help tools to support production-level output for 
        these output formats: Eclipse help with plugin support, HTML Help, and 
        JavaHelp. Also other new help formats as prioritized for this release 
        (such as manpage, QT Assistant, etc.). (roughly the 1.2 plan, based on 
        OASIS DITA 1.0-level DTDs and Schemas with any fixes known at that 
        point)</li> <li>1.3 (roughly): Develop migrators for OASIS updates that 
        might impact existing DITA source. Other requirements as identified, 
        such as styling layers, custom package building from the project, 
        interfaces to translation standards such as XLIFF, and so forth.</li> 
        </ul></p>
      <p>The project will use the SourceForge RFE tool to accept new 
        requirements. These will be prioritized for placement into plan 
        according to the process in the Development Process document.</p>
    </section>
  </conbody>
</concept>