<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- This file is part of the DITA Open Toolkit project hosted on 
     Sourceforge.net. See the accompanying license.txt file for 
     applicable licenses.-->
<!-- (c) Copyright IBM Corp. 2004, 2005 All Rights Reserved. -->

<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Reference//EN" "reference.dtd">

<reference id="runant" xml:lang="en-us">
  <title>Running Ant</title>
  <titlealts>
    <navtitle>Running Ant</navtitle>
  </titlealts>
  <shortdesc>After setting up the Ant environment, you can build the DITA 
    output by running <codeph>ant</codeph> command. </shortdesc>
  <refbody>
    <example>Here are some samples to explain how to use Ant to build sample 
      output in the DITA directory. <note> To run the Ant demo properly, you 
      should switch to the <b>DITA installation directory</b> under the command 
      prompt. </note><ul> <li>You can build all demos in the DITA 
      directory.<p>Input <codeph>ant all</codeph></p><p>The building process 
      will create an <b>/out/</b> directory and puts the output files in 
      subdirectories that parallel the source directory. </p></li> <li>You can 
      also rebuild specific part of output of the DITA sample files.<p>You need 
      to remove part of the output first by specifying a 
      "<codeph>clean</codeph>" target, and then rebuild the output. For 
      example: To rebuild FAQ demo, input</p><p><codeph>ant 
      clean.demo.faq</codeph></p><p><codeph>ant demo.faq</codeph></p><note>To 
      find out the complete list of targets you can clean and build, check the 
      <i>name</i> attributes for the target elements within the 
      <i>build.xml</i> file. Or, input <codeph>ant -projecthelp</codeph> for 
      information.</note> </li> <li>You can also build assigned input to output 
      in a default and easy way. <p>Input <codeph>ant</codeph></p><p>Ant will 
      prompt you for the input and output, and you need to input the 
      directories of input files and output with correctly upper or lower case. 
      </p></li> </ul><p>You can reuse the targets provided by the 
      <i>conductor.xml</i> file in builds for your own DITA content by coping 
      the<i> build.xml, conductor.xml, pretargets.xml, ditatargets.xml</i> and 
      <i>catalog-ant.xml </i>files into a new directory and edit the 
      <i>build.xml</i> to specify your DITA files. Refer to <xref 
      href="DITA-antscript.xml">Ant tasks and 
      tweaks</xref> for more information of those functions.</p><note>To 
      troubleshoot problems in setting up Java, Ant, Saxon, or FOP, you will 
      get better information from the communities for those components rather 
      than the communities for the DITA. Of course, if you find issues relevant 
      to the DITA XSLT scripts (or have ideas for improving them), you are 
      encouraged to engage the DITA community.</note> </example>
  </refbody>
</reference>