<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!-- (C) Copyright IBM Corporation 2001, 2004. All Rights Reserved.
 | This file is part of the DITA package on IBM's developerWorks site.
 | See license.txt for disclaimers and permissions.
 *-->
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../xsl/dita2html_shell.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE reference PUBLIC "-//IBM//DTD DITA Reference//EN" "../../dtd/reference.dtd" []>
<reference id="table2" xml:lang="en-us">
   <title>Table elements</title>
   <refbody>
      <section>
         <p>DITA topics support two types of tables. One is the most common table format
used in industry, the &lt;<apiname>CALS table</apiname>&gt; (or more recently known also
as the Oasis Table Exchange Model). The CALS table supports the spanning of
multiple rows or columns for special layout or organizational needs, and provides
a wide variety of controls over the display properties of the data and even
the table structure itself.<indexterm>Table elements</indexterm>
         
         </p>
         <p>The other table structure in DITA is called &lt;<apiname>simpletable</apiname>&gt;. As
the name implies, it is structurally less sophisticated than the CALS table,
and can be used as a very simple, regular table for which close control of
formatting is not as important. However, the main advantage of simpletable
is for describing lists of data with regular headings, such as telephone directory
listings, display adapter configuration data, or API properties. If you have
ever needed a "three-part definition list," simpletable is used for that purpose.</p>
         <p>Upon output, the CALS table is often fully reproduced using presentation
hints contained in the markup itself (such as specific column widths or span
controls). The simpletable has a similar, table-like output, but it is more
adaptable for dynamic, in-browser data viewports that show one set (row or
column) of information at a time, with controls for "paging" through the data.</p>
      </section>
   </refbody>
</reference>