<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Arbortext, Inc., 1988-2010, v.4002-->
<!DOCTYPE concept PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Concept//EN"
 "..\dtd\concept.dtd">
<?Pub Sty _display FontColor="red"?>
<concept id="usingparameterbuildingtool" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Running DITA-OT from command-line tool</title>
<shortdesc>The DITA Open Toolkit provides a command-line tool as an alternative for users with
    little knowledge of Ant. Most parameters available to the Ant builds are also available using
    the command-line tool.</shortdesc>
<conbody>
<note type="important">The command-line tool interface is simply a wrapper around the Ant interface;
      it takes the simplified parameters as input, converts them to Ant parameters, and then runs an
      Ant build. This means that applications embedding the toolkit should always invoke Ant
      directly. For individual builds, the additional Java overhead is minimal, but for repeated or
      server based builds, it the extra memory usage will become more of an issue.</note>
<section>       <title>Running command-line tool</title><p>If you
are using the "Full Easy Install" package, running the startcmd batch
file will set up a build environment for you and put you in the correct
directory. If you are not using this method, you must set up all of
your tools (Ant, XSLT, FOP, etc) before running the build.</p><ol>
<li>Change into the DITA Open Toolkit installation directory.</li>
<li>On the command-line, enter the following command:
          <codeblock>java -jar lib/dost.jar /i:samples/sequence.ditamap /outdir:out /transtype:xhtml</codeblock></li>
</ol><p>This particular example calls Ant to build the sample <filepath>sequence.ditamap</filepath> file
        to XHTML. The output is placed in the <filepath>out/</filepath> directory.</p><p>Note:         <ol>
<li>In this example, the character slash preceded by a space is the
separator for each parameter.</li>
<li>Currently, the parameters <codeph>/filter</codeph>, <codeph>/ftr</codeph>,
             <codeph>/hdr</codeph>, and <codeph>/hdf</codeph> require
an absolute path.</li>
<li>The properties file is saved in the <codeph>${args.logdir}</codeph> directory. The following
            command provides an example using this properties file:
            <codeblock>ant -propertyfile ${args.logdir}/property.temp</codeblock>
          </li>
<li>To see a list of all supported parameters from the command-line tool, run the following command
            with no additional parameters:<codeblock>java -jar lib/dost.jar</codeblock></li>
</ol></p>     </section>
<section>       <title>Supported parameters</title>
  <p>See <xref href="dita-ot_java_properties.dita"/> for supported command-line tool arguments. To
        get a full list of arguments, run</p>
  <codeblock>java -jar lib/dost.jar -help</codeblock>
</section>
<section>       <title>Command-line help</title>       <p> You can find the version of toolkit and the usage of the command-line from the command
        line help by using the following commands:
        <codeblock>java -jar lib/dost.jar <b>-version</b>
java -jar lib/dost.jar <b>-h</b>        </codeblock></p>       <p>You can see the brief description of the supported parameters in the command-line window
        when you type a specified command.</p>     </section>
</conbody>
</concept>
<?Pub *0000013750?>
