<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
 "topic.dtd">
<?Pub Sty _display FontColor="red"?>
<?Pub Inc?>
<topic id="fixesandfeatures" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Feature requests and defect reports</title>
<shortdesc>Feature requests and defect reports can be submitted at any time through the project page
at GitHub. </shortdesc>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<keywords>
<indexterm>DITA-OT project<indexterm>defect reports</indexterm><indexterm>feature
requests</indexterm></indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<p>The core project contributors track and address bugs reported against the project; they issue
patches based on urgency. The core contributors also will provide feedback on requests for new
features or design changes, but they might not be able to provide development assistance.</p>
<p>All new bug reports or feature requests should be submitted through
github: <xref keyref="dita-ot-issues"></xref>.</p>
<section><title>Feature requests</title><p>The project committers periodically review new feature requests with contributors and interested
parties; when possible, they make plans to implement the new features.</p><p>If an existing project contributor is interested in a new request, the item is assigned to the
contributor and implemented based on the contributor's schedule. Otherwise, if the request is valid
and in line with project goals, it is left open for an interested party to pick up and implement.
Some requests are best implemented as a plug-in rather than in the core DITA-OT code; in those
cases, project committers suggest alternatives and close the request.</p></section>
<section><title>Defect reports</title><p>The project committers determine the owner of the relevant components and assign the defect to
the component owner for validation and disposition. Responses, fixes, and workarounds are issued
faster if the defect report includes sample files and clear instructions for reproducing the
issue.</p><p>If bugs are found in the OASIS DITA DTDs or Schemas, they are fixed in the toolkit and reported
to the OASIS DITA Technical Committee.</p></section>
</body><?Pub Caret -2?>
</topic>
<?Pub *0000002220?>
