<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN"
 "topic.dtd">
<?Pub Inc?>
<topic id="projectroles" xml:lang="en-us">
<title>Project roles and responsibilities</title>
<titlealts>
<navtitle>Project roles</navtitle>
</titlealts>
<shortdesc>The DITA Open Toolkit (DITA-OT) project has the following roles: Project manager,
committer, and contributor. Each role has different rights and obligations.</shortdesc>
<prolog>
<metadata>
<keywords>
<indexterm>DITA-OT project<indexterm>project roles</indexterm></indexterm>
</keywords>
</metadata>
</prolog>
<body>
<dl>
<dlentry>
<dt>Project manager (PM)</dt>
<dd>
<p>The project manager is responsible for managing the project. The PM provides leadership to guide
the overall direction of the project and removes obstacles, solves problems, and resolves conflicts.
The PM works to ensure that the following goals are met:<ul>
<li>The project operates effectively.</li>
<li>All project plans, technical documents, and reports are publicly available.</li>
<li>The project operates using the open-source rules of engagement, which stress meritocracy,
transparency, and open participation.
<!--These principles work together. Anyone can participate in this project. This open interaction, from answering questions to reporting bugs to making code contributions to creating designs, enables everyone to recognize and utilize the contributions.--></li>
</ul></p>
</dd>
</dlentry>
<dlentry>
<dt>Committer</dt>
<dd>Committers oversee the quality and originality of all contributions. Committers influences the
development of the project and have write access to the source-code repository. This position
reflects a track record of high-quality contributions to the project. </dd>
</dlentry>
<dlentry>
<dt>Contributor</dt>
<dd>Contributors contribute code, documentation, fixes, tests, or other work to the project.
Contributors do not have write access to the source-code repository. There is no limit to the scope
of such contributions, though contributors who expect to donate a large amount of new function to
the project are encouraged to work with committers in advance.</dd>
</dlentry>
</dl>
</body>
</topic><?Pub Caret -3?>
<?Pub *0000002130?>
